Finding Aid for the Augustus F. Hawkins papers LSC.1642
UCLA Library Special Collections
Augustus F. Hawkins papers
1935-1990
UCLA Library Special Collections
Hawkins, Augustus F
LSC.1642
137 linear feet (137 cartons)
1 oversize box
Augustus Freeman Hawkins (1907- ) was a member of the California State Assembly (1935-63) a Democrat in the U.S. Congress (1963-91), Chairman of the Committee on House Administration (1981-84), Chairman of the Committee on Education and Labor (98th-101st Congresses), and a member of many Congressional Committees. He retired from public service in 1990. The collection consists of materials documenting Hawkins' service as a U.S. Congressman from 1963-90 and as Chairman of the House Education and Labor Committee from 1984-90. A small portion of the collection relates to his service as a California State Assemblyman.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Augustus F. Hawkins, 1990.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9917204033606533
Biography
Augustus Freeman Hawkins was born in Shreveport, Louisiana, on August 31, 1907; his family moved to Los Angeles in 1918; AB, UCLA, 1931; graduated from USC, 1932; member, California State Assembly, 1935-63; Democrat, U.S. Congress, 1963-91; Chairman, Committee on House Administration, 1981-84; Chairman, Committee on Education and Labor (98th-101st Congresses); member, Joint Economic Committee, 1984-90; member, Joint Committee on Printing, 1977-84; member, Joint Committee on the Library, 1981-84; retired from public service in 1990.
Biographical Narrative
Augustus F. Hawkins was born August 31, 1907, in Shreveport, Louisiana. At age eleven his family moved to Los Angeles, California, where he later attended Jefferson High School, graduated from the University of California at Los Angeles with a degree in Economics, and attended graduate school at the University of Southern California.
Congressman Hawkins represented south, central Los Angeles for fifty-six years. He served from 1935 to 1962 in the California State Assembly before coming to Washington in 1963 as a member of the United States House of Representatives. He will retire from elected public service at the end of 1990.
He has compiled a remarkable record of legislative achievement. As a State Assemblyman he authored over 100 laws, including many important social welfare and anti-discrimination bills. As a United States Congressman, he has enacted legislation in the areas of child care; elementary, secondary, vocational and higher education; job training and employment; and Civil Rights. Significant bills passed into public law include the Civil Rights Act Amendment establishing the Equal Employment opportunity Commission, 1975; the Comprehensive Employment and Training Act Amendments, 1978; the Full Employment and Balanced Growth (Humphrey-Hawkins) Act, 1978; the Job Training partnership Act, 1982; the School Improvement (Hawkins-Stafford) Act, 1988; and the Civil Rights Restoration Act, 1988.
Prior to his chairmanship of the Education and Labor Committee, Congressman Hawkins served as chairman of the House Administration Committee from 1981 to 1984, where he was responsible for House of Representatives procurement, personnel, printing, elections, and automation issues. Additionally, he served as a member of the Joint Economic Committee from 1984 to 1990, the Joint Committee on Printing from 1977 to 1984, and the Joint Committee on the Library from 1981 to 1984.
Congressman Hawkins' view of public service is best expressed by his own words: The leadership belongs not to the loudest, not to those who beat the drums or blow the trumpets, but to those who day in and day out, in all seasons, work for the practical realization of a better world --those who have the stamina to persist and to remain dedicated. To those belong the leadership.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials documenting Augustus F. Hawkins's lengthy service as a U.S. Congressman representing South Central Los Angeles from 1963-90 and as Chairman of the House Education and Labor Committee from 1984-90. A small portion of the collection relates to his service as a California State Assemblyman, 1935-62. Materials in the collection cover subjects such as Civil Rights, employment, child care, and equal opportunity with respect to education and job training.
Expanded Scope and Content
The papers of Congressman Augustus F. Hawkins include materials documenting his lengthy service as an United States Congressman representing south, central Los Angeles from 1963 to 1990 and as the Chairman of the Education and Labor Committee from 1984 to 1990. A small amount of material relates to his service as a California state Assemblyman from 1935 to 1962.
In the collection are Legislative Files, Subject Files, Correspondence Files, District Office Files, Education and Labor Committee Files, California State Assembly Files, and Miscellaneous Material. The papers cover subjects such as civil rights, employment, equal opportunity, education, job training, and child care. The two series with perhaps the greatest research value are the legislative files since they document Congressman Hawkins' attempts to enact legislation and his Committee service, and the subject files which provide the background information, including his handwritten notes, for many of his legislative efforts.
During the last year, approximately 200 boxes of inactive files of the Washington and district offices and numerous filing cabinets and boxes of Education and Labor Committee staff files were reviewed to determine historical value. Of this total, over 130 boxes were retained for the archives. Duplicates, publications, routine files, and other materials were discarded.
The papers are arranged by series (or type). A minimum amount of arrangement was done within each series. Each type of material is described in a series description (a narrative with accompanying box lists or box and folder lists). Individual folder listings were compiled for most of the series and were taken directly from folder labels. The number in parentheses after a folder listing indicates when more than one folder exists for a particular topic. Since similar materials could not always be packed together, numbered boxes are sometimes listed out of order. Asterisks denote when a box containing more than one type of material appears on the list more than once. Additionally, box counts given at the beginning of each series are not the actual number of boxes in that series but rather a total of the number of boxes containing that type of material. The table of contents below refers researchers to individual series descriptions.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Legislative files (39 Boxes).
Subject files (31 Boxes).
Correspondence files (10 Boxes).
District office files (39 Boxes).
Education and Labor Committee files (17 Boxes).
California State Assembly files (2 Boxes).
Miscellaneous (11 Boxes).
Related Material
Black Leadership in Los Angeles: Augustus F. Hawkins [oral history transcript] / Augustus F. Hawkins, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1995. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitaized and are available online through Calisphere: Hawkins (Augustus F.) Papers (88 items)
UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research Interview of Augustus F. Hawkins (1988)
UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research Interview of Augustus F. Hawkins (1992)
African American legislators -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; United States. Congress. House; California. Legislature. Assembly; Hawkins, Augustus F.--Archives.; United States--Congress--House--Committee on Education and Labor.
- Legislative Files, 1963-1990; (Contained in 39 Boxes)
  Scope and Contents note
  Included in the Legislative Files are lists of bills sponsored and cosponsored by Congressman Hawkins, bill files, Committee files, and a few subject files. Preceding the bill files are bill listings compiled by office staff and staff of the Congressional Research Service of the Library of Congress. For the 88th through 92nd Congresses, there are pages from the gongressional Record Index which list where in the Record to find information about bills and resolutions introduced by the Congressman. The CRS listings, beginning with the 93rd Congress, describe the bill and any action taken. Additionally, there are CRS listings found within each Congress that may duplicate information found at the beginning of the series.
  In most cases, the actual bill files simply contain a copy of the bill or resolution. A few other bill files also contain related materials such as bill drafts, companion and related bills from the House and Senate, Committee reports, floor statements, press releases, dear colleague and other letters from members of Congress, correspondence from constituents and others interested in legislation, analyses of bills, newsclippings, memos, and other types of material. Interestingly, in the bill files concerning Watergate, all of the constituent correspondence supports impeaching President Richard Nixon. It is unclear if the Hawkins office received any constituent correspondence supporting the former President.
  Committee files primarily include correspondence from constituents and others on legislative matters before Committees. Also included are dear colleague and other letters from members to Congressman Hawkins, Committee reports, bills, memos, press releases, floor statements, Committee agenda, bill drafts, newsclippings, Committee testimony, and hearing reports. Miscellaneous Committee files contain correspondence about Senate bills, House bills not yet under consideration, and issues for which there was no pending legislation.
  The Education and Labor Committee files contain constituent correspondence; correspondence from other members of Congress, state and local officials, and others with an interest in legislation; bills; Committee reports; lists of activities of members of the Committee; summaries of major legislative actions of the Committee; copies of letters and memos to and from former Chairman Carl Perkins; floor statements; staff memos to Chairman Hawkins; Committee testimony; bill analyses; floor remarks; newsclippings; lists of Committee members; and other materials. Materials documenting Congressman Hawkins chairmanship of the Equal Opportunities SubCommittee from 1977 to 1984, include correspondence from him to other subCommittee members, hearing reports, minutes of mark-up sessions, lists of witnesses, press releases, and weekly and monthly reports during the 94th Congress.
  A few subject files are found throughout this series. The largest and most notable group are found within the 93rd Congress and concern legislation sponsored by Congressman Hawkins to rectify a 1906 Brownsville, Texas incident where approximately 170 black soldiers, blamed by townspeople for a local crime, were dishonorably discharged from the army without evidence to prove their guilt and without a trial. Congressman Hawkins' bill changed the military record of each man to reflect an honorable discharge and provided compensation to any living survivors or their widows. These files contain bills; background material; a Senate bill and report; drafts of legislation; correspondence between members of Congress; Congressman Hawkins' correspondence with the Army Department and Veterans Administration, widows of servicemen, the media, and John Weaver, the author of a book on the subject; press releases; floor statements; newsclippings; and other materials.
  At the end of the files for the 99th Congress are a few miscellaneous Committee files documenting the work of the House Administration Committee, of which Congressman Hawkins was chair from 1981 to 1984, and two other panels he belonged to -- the Joint Committee on the Library and the Joint Committee on Printing.
  The Legislative Files were found broadly arranged by term of Congress. within each term of Congress, the bill files were separated into bills sponsored and cosponsored and within each, the files were either alphabetical by bill title or numerical by bill number. The Committee files were generally alphabetical by name of Committee.
  - Lists of Bills Sponsored and Cosponsored
    - 88th-91st Congresses. (Box 1)
    - 88th-92nd Congresses. (Box 1)
    - 92nd Congress. (Box 1)
    - 93rd Congress. (Box 1)
  - Record of Legislative Activity, 1963-1990
    General note
    (Compiled by Congressional Research Service)
    - 88th-92nd Congresses, Congressional Record Index. (Box 23*)
    - 93rd Congress
      - Bills Sponsored. (Box 23*)
      - Bills Cosponsored. (Box 23*)
    - 94th Congress
      - Bills Sponsored. (Box 24)
      - Bills Cosponsored. (Box 24)
    - 95th Congress
      - Bills Sponsored. (Box 24)
      - Amendments Sponsored. (Box 24)
      - Bills Cosponsored. (Box 24)
    - 96th Congress
      - Bills Sponsored. (Box 24)
      - Bills Cosponsored. (Box 24)
    - 97th Congress
      - Bills Sponsored. (Box 24)
      - Bills Cosponsored. (Box 24)
    - 98th Congress
      - Bills Sponsored. (Box 24)
      - Bills Cosponsored. (Box 24)
      - Bills Cosponsored. (Box 25)
    - 99th Congress
      - Bills Sponsored. (Box 25)
      - Bills Cosponsored (2). (Box 25)
    - 100th Congress
      - Bills Sponsored. (Box 25)
      - Bills Cosponsored (2). (Box 25)
    - 101st Congress
      - Bills and Amendments Sponsored. (Box 26*)
      - Bills Cosponsored. (Box 26*)
  - 88th Congress, (1963-1964)
    - Bills Sponsored. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 3600, Junipero Serra Commemoration. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 3953, Military Discharge Review. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 4030, Federal Aid to Elementary and Secondary Schools. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 4031, Equal Employment Opportunity Act. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 4032, Equal Pay Act. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 5202, Military Discharge Review (same as H.R. 3953). (Box 74)
      - H.R. 5203, Area Redevelopment Act Amendment. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 5204, U.S. Commission on Aging. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 5205, Manpower and Training Act Amendment, Matching Requirements. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 5266, Hospital Insurance Act. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 5632, National Service Corps. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6063, Manpower Development and Training Act Amendment, Youth Training. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6288, Prohibits Financial Assistance to Programs that Discriminate. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6327, Public School Desegregation Act. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6328, Prohibits Financial Aid to Schools that Discriminate. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6329, Hill-Burton Anti-Discrimination Amendment. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6330, Hospital Anti-Discrimination Amendment. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6331 (same as H.R. 6288). (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6332, Constitutional Rights Protection. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6333, Act Against Discrimination (Equal Rights). (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6334, Anti-Violence. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6335, Literacy Tests. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6336, Civil Rights Act Amendments. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 6972, National Defense Education Act. (Box 74)
      - Amendments (Anti-Discrimination). (Box 74)
      - H.R. 7596, Social Security Act Amendments (Benefit Increase). (Box 74)
      - H.R. 8188, Immigration and Nationality Act Amendments. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 8352, Private Enterprise Amendment. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 9559, Cooperative Housing. (Box 74)
      - H.R. 11370, Water Resources Development. (Box 74)
      - H.Con.Res. 151, Baltic States Resolution. (Box 74)
      - H.J.Res. 522, National Health Week. (Box 74)
      - H.J.Res. 1053, Apportionment Amendment. (Box 74)
      - H.Res. 690, Religious Persecution in Soviet Union. (Box 74)
    - Bills Introduced. (Box 74)
    - Committee Files
      - Agriculture Committee
        - Bracero Program, P.L. 78. (Box 74)
          - Resolution regarding the future of the Mexican Agricultural Worker Importation Program (Public Law 78 -- 82nd Congress), 1960-02-25 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 May 9, San Francisco, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-05-09 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 May 22, San Francisco, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., 1963-05-22 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 May 23, Los Angeles, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-05-23 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 May 27, New York, N.Y. to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-05-27 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 July 28, Coachella, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-07-28 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 July 29, San Leandro, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-07-29 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 July 29, Planada, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-07-29 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 September 1, South Gate, California to the Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-09-01 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 September 3, Orange, California to Honorable Congressman Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-09-03 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 September 6, Glendale, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-09-06 (Box 74)
          - Telegram, 1963 September 8, Los Angeles, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-09-08 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 October 14, Saratoga, California to Honorable Gus Hawkins, M. C., Washington D.C., 1963-10-14 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 October 22, to Mr. R.V. Garrod, Saratoga, California, 1963-10-22 (Box 74)
        - Farm Program. (Box 74)
      - Appropriations Committee. (Box 74)
      - Armed Services Committee. (Box 74)
      - Banking and Currency Committee. (Box 74)
        - Banking and Currency, Area Redevelopment Act. (Box 74)
      - District of Columbia Committee. (Box 74)
      - Education and Labor Committee
        - Equal Pay Bill, H.R. 6060. (Box 74)
        - Federal Aid, H.R. 3000. (Box 74)
        - Federally Impacted Areas, P.L. 815 and 874. (Box 74)
        - Higher Education Bill, H.R. 6143. (Box 74)
        - Labor Laws. (Box 74)
        - Library Services Act. (Box 74)
        - Manpower Development and Training Act. (Box 74)
        - Miscellaneous Education Bills. (Box 74)
        - Vocational Education, H.R. 4955. (Box 74)
      - Foreign Affairs Committee
        - Miscellaneous. (Box 74)
        - Nuclear Test Ban Treaty. (Box 74)
      - Interior and Insular Affairs Committee. (Box 74)
      - Interstate and Foreign Commerce Committee. (Box 74)
      - Interstate and Foreign Commerce
        - Freight Rates, H.R. 4700. (Box 74)
        - Medical School Aid, H.R. 12. (Box 74)
        - Railroad Dispute. (Box 74)
      - Judiciary Committee
        - Miscellaneous. (Box 74)
        - Civil Rights. (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 September 26, Santa Ana, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-09-26 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 November, Los Angeles, California to Honorable Mr. Edwards, Washington, D.C., 1963-11 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 December 5, Washington, D.C. to Miss Sylvia Evans, Los Angeles, California, 1963-12-05 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 August 15, Los Angeles, California to Honorable Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-08-15 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 September 4, Washington, D.C. to Miss Nellie M. Craig, Los Angeles, California, 1963-09-04 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 June 12, Los Angeles, California to Augustus F. Hawkins, Washington, D.C., 1963-06-12 (Box 74)
          - Letter, 1963 June 26, Washington, D.C. to Mrs. Mary L. Mitchell, Los Angeles, California, 1963-06-26 (Box 74)
      - Post Office and Civil Service Committee. (Box 74)
      - Rules Committee. (Box 74)
      - Un-American Activities Committee. (Box 74)
      - Veterans Affairs Committee. (Box 74)
      - Ways and Means Committee. (Box 74)
      - Ways and Means Committee
        - Excise Taxes. (Box 74)
        - Income Tax. (Box 74)
        - Social Security. (Box 74)
        - Tax Reduction. (Box 74)
      - Administrative, Los Angeles County. (Box 75)
      - Administrative, State of California. (Box 75)
  - 88th-89th Congresses (), 1963-66
    - Bills Sponsored. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6333, Act Against Discrimination (Equal Rights). (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6828, American Indian Day. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6334, Anti-Violence (Improvement of State and Local Justice Act). (Box 75)
      - H.J. Res. 1053, Apportionment Amendment. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 4397, Area Redevelopment Act Amendments. (Box 75)
      - H.Con. Res. 289, Baltic States Independence. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6336, Civil Rights Act Amendments. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 4952, Civil Rights, Literacy Tests. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 5204, Commission on Aging. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6332, Constitutional Rights Protection. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 9559, Cooperative Housing. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 8972, Cotton Allotments. (Box 75)
      - H.J.Res. 559, Electrical Equipment. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 4031, Equal Employment Opportunity Act. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 4032, Equal Pay Act. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 13743, Fair Labor Standards Act. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 10065, Fair Employment Practices Commission. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 4030, Federal Aid to Elementary and Secondary Schools. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6328, Financial Aid Prohibition to Schools that Discriminate. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6288, Financial Assistance Prohibition to Programs that Discriminate. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6330, Hospital Anti-Discrimination Amendment. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 5266, Hospital Insurance Act. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6329, Hill-Burton Anti-Discrimination Amendment. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 8188, Immigration and Nationality Act Amendments. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 14785, Interstate Compact Between Arizona and California. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 17435, Income Tax Deductions for Teachers. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 15922, Insurance on Loans (OEO Amendment). (Box 75)
      - H.R. 13622, Library Services and Construction Act. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6335, Literacy Tests. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 4691, Lower Colorado River Basin Project. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6063, Manpower Development and Training Act, Youth Tralnlng Amendment. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 5205, Manpower and Training Act Amendment, Matching Requirements. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 10014, Members' Office Space. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 3953, H.R. 5202, Military Discharge Review (2). (Box 75)
      - H.R. 11836, Minority Groups Sculpture. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6972, National Defense Education Act Amendments (Anti-Discrimination). (Box 75)
      - H.J. Res. 522, National Health Week. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 368, National Humanities Foundation. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 5632, National Service Corps. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 10014, Office Space in Districts, 89-1. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 12979, Older Americans Act Amendments, 1966. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 3575, Padre Junipero Serra Commemoration. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 14098, Postal Field Service. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 8352, Private Enterprise Amendment. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6327, Public School Desegregation Act. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 11188, Public Works and Economic Development Act Amendments, 89-1. (Box 75)
      - H.J. Res. 820, Rail Transportation, Multi-State Authority, 89-1. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 12208, Redwood National Park, 89-2. (Box 75)
      - H.Con.Res. 269, Religious Persecution in Soviet Union. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 6829, Social Security Act. (Box 75)
      - H.R. 7596, Social Security Act Amendments (Benefit Increase). (Box 75)
      - H.R. 4878, Solid Waste Disposal Act. (Box 75)